It’s 1526 in what is now Northern India,
Günümüzün Kuzey Hindistan’ında yıl 1526
and Sultan Ibrahim Lodhi is about to face off against a prince
ve Sultan İbrahim Ludî Orta Asyalı bir prensle
from Central Asia, Zahiruddin Muhammad Babur.
Zahîreddîn Muhammed Bâbur’le yüzleşmek üzere.
To quash the threat, the Sultan brings his war elephants to battle.
Tehditi ortadan kaldırmak için Sultan savaşa fillerini de getiriyor.
But it’s said that the explosions of Babur’s cannons and muskets
Ancak Babür’ün top ve tüfek patlamalarının filleri ürküttüğü
startled the elephants and they trampled the Sultan’s own army.
ve Sultan’ın kendi ordusunu ezip geçtiği söylendi.
Babur had long harbored ambitions of building his own empire.
Babür’ün uzun süre kendi imparatorluğunu kurma hırsı vardı.
Though he was descended from some of the world’s most successful conquerors,
Dünyanın en başarılı fatihlerinin soyundan gelse de
he struggled to gain a foothold
Orta Asya’da birçok hırslı prens arasında
So he turned his attention to India,
Bu yüzden dikkatini Hindistan’a çevirdi.
where his descendants stayed and built the Mughal Empire,
torunlarının Babür İmparatorluğunu kurduğu yer,
one of the wealthiest and most powerful states in the early modern world
eski modern dünyada en varlıklı ve en güçlü devletlerden biri
and home to nearly a quarter of the global population.
ve dünya nüfusunun yaklaşık dörtte birine ev sahipliği yapmaktadır.
Babur died just four years after that fateful battle,
Babür bu önemli savaşın ardından hemen öldü
but his own memoirs and the work of his descendants
ancak onun kendi anıları ve torunlarının gayreti
immortalized him in colorful fashion.
onu renkli bir şekilde ölümsüzleştirdi.
His daughter, Gulbadan, recalled in her own memoir how Babur—
Kızı Gulbadan, kendi anılarında Babur’un nasıl—
having recently given up drinking—
yakın zamanda içki bırakmasını—
filled a newly-constructed pool with lemonade rather than wine.
yeni yapılan havuzu şarap yerine limonata ile doldurdu.
His grandson, Akbar, commissioned exquisite miniature paintings
Torunu Ekber, Babür hikayelerini kişiye özel minyatür boyacılığı yapmakla
of Babur’s stories—
görevlendirildi—
one depicted the empire’s founder riding through his camp,
biri imparatorluğun kurucusunu sarhoşken atının üzerinde yığılıp kalmış
drunkenly slumped over his horse.
bir şekilde kampın içinden geçerken resmetti.
It was Akbar who consolidated Mughal power.
Babür’ün gücünü sağlamlaştıran Ekberdi.
He established protections for peasants—
Köylüler için koruma tesis etti—
which in turn increased their productivity and generated more tax revenue—
Bu da üretkenliği artırdı ve daha fazla vergi geliri sağladı—
and embarked on military campaigns to expand Mughal territory.
ve Babür topraklarını genişletmek için askeri kampanyalara girişti.
Princes who swore allegiance to him were rewarded,
Ona biat eden prensler ödüllendirildi,
while he made brutal examples of those who resisted,
direnenlerin acımasız örneklerini verirken,
killing them and many of their subjects.
onları ve tebaalarını öldürüyordu.
His conquests opened access to port cities on the Indian Ocean,
Hint Okyanusunda, fetihleri liman şehirlerine ulaşımı açtı,
which connected the Mughals to Arab, Chinese, Ottoman, and European traders,
Babürleri Arap, Çinli, Osmanlı ve Avrupalı tüccarlara bağlayan,
bringing in incalculable wealth,
çok büyük zenginlik getiren,
including silver and new crops from the Americas.
Amerika’dan gümüş ve yeni mahsuller dahil.
As the Muslim ruler of a diverse, multiethnic empire,
Çeşitli, çok ırklı bir imparatorluğun Müslüman bir hükümdarı olarak
Akbar worked to create internal cohesion by appointing members
Ekber, Hindu çoğunluğun üyelerini
of the Hindu majority to high positions in his government,
hükümetinde yüksek mevkilere atayarak,
marrying a Hindu bride,
Hindu bir gelinle evlenerek
and distributing translated copies of the “Mahabharata,”
ve Müslüman soylularına yazdığı eski bir Hint destanı şiiri
an ancient Indian epic poem, to his Muslim nobles.
“Mahabharata”nın çevrilmiş kopyalarını dağıtarak iç uyum yaratmaya çalıştı.
Akbar also hosted lively religious debates where Sunni and Shia Muslims,
Ayrıca Ekber, Sünni ve Şii Müslümanlar,
Hindus, Jains, Zoroastrians,
Hindular, Jainler, Zerdüştlerin
and the newly arrived Portuguese Jesuit missionaries
ve yeni gelen Portekizli Cizvit misyonerler, kendi inançlarının
defended the merits of their respective faiths.
erdemlerini savundukları dini tartışmalara ev sahipliği yaptılar.
While most participants viewed this as an intellectual exercise,
Çoğu katılımcı bunu entelektüel bir egzersiz olarak görürken
Portuguese missionaries were disappointed by their failure to convert Akbar.
Portekizli misyonerler, Ekber’i dinine döndürme başarısızlığıyla
The Mughals built architectural masterpieces
Babürler,
such as the Taj Mahal and the Red Fort,
Tac Mahal ve Kızıl Kale gibi
a palace three kilometers around, that housed 50,000 people
50 bin kişiyi barındıran üç kilometrelik bir saray ve muhteşem altın
and contained the magnificent gold and jewel-encrusted Peacock Throne.
ve mücevherlerle kaplı Tavus Kuşu Tahtı’nı içeren mimari şaheserler inşa etti.
Just the throne took seven years to construct.
Sadece tahtın inşası yedi yıl sürdü.
During its first 180 years, the Mughals had only six rulers,
İlk 180 yıl boyunca Babürlerin yalnızca altı hükümdarı oldu,
which contributed to the empire’s stability.
bu da imparatorluğun istikrarına katkıda bulundu.
When the fourth emperor, Jahangir,
Dördüncü imparator Cihangir,
struggled with alcohol and opioid addiction,
alkol ve opioid bağımlılığı ile mücadele ederken
his wife, Nur Jahan, took the reins as co-ruler.
eşi Nur Cihan, eş hükümdar olarak kontrolü eline aldı.
When a traitorous general captured her husband in an attempted coup,
Hain bir general, kocasını darbe girişiminde yakaladığında
she negotiated his release and rallied the army to stop the rebellion.
serbest bırakılması için pazarlık yaptı ve isyanı durdurmak için orduyu topladı.
She once led a hunting party to track down a tiger that was terrorizing a village,
Bir keresinde bir köye terör estiren bir kaplanın izini sürmek için
leading one poet to write:
Bir şairi yazmaya yönlendiriyor.
“Though Nur Jahan be in form of a woman/ In the ranks of men she’s a tiger-slayer.”
“Nur Cihan bir kadın şeklinde olsa da/ erkekler safında o bir kaplan avcısı.”
Following the death of the sixth emperor, Aurangzeb, in 1707,
Altıncı imparator Alemgir’in 1707′de ölümünün ardından,
seven emperors took the throne over the next 21 years.
sonraki 21 yıl boyunca yedi hükümdar daha tahta geçti.
These frequent transitions of power reflected
Bu sık güç değişimleri
the larger political, economic, social, and environmental crises
18. yüzyıl boyunca imparatorluğu rahatsız eden
In response to this turmoil,
Bu hengameye cevaben,
regional leaders started refusing to pay taxes and broke away from Mughal control.
bölge liderleri, vergileri ödemeyi reddetmeye
The British East India Company offered military support to these regional rulers,
İngiliz Doğu Hindistan Şirketi,
which in turn increased the company's political influence,
Bu da şirketin politik etkisini artırdı.
enabling it to eventually take direct control of Bengal,
Nihayet Hindistan’daki en zengin bölgelerden birisi olan Bengal’in
one of the wealthiest regions in India.
doğrudan kontrolünü ele almasına sağladı.
By the 19th century, the East India Company had massive political influence
19. yüzyılda, Doğu Hindistan Şirketi, büyük bir siyasi etkiye
and a large standing army, which included Indian troops.
ve Hindistan askeri birliklerinin de dahil sürekli orduya sahipti.
When these troops revolted in 1857,
1857′de bu birlikler ayaklandığında
aiming to force out the British and restore Mughal influence,
İngilizleri zorla göndermeyi ve Babür etkisini onarmayı amaçlıyorlardı
the British government intervened,
İngiliz hükümeti müdahale etti,
replacing company rule with direct colonial rule,
Şirket kurallarını doğrudan koloni kurallarıyla değiştirerek
deposing the last Mughal emperor and sending him into exile.
son Babür hükümdarını tahttan indirerek sürgüne gönderdi.
And so, over three centuries after its founding,
Böylece, kuruluşundan üç asır sonra
the Mughal Empire came to an end.
Babür İmparatorluğu sonlandı.